Guide to the John Rodman Paul Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Rodman Paul papers
1920-1992
1920-1971
MS 1333
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.25
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, topical files, photographs, and journals associated with the academic and epidemiological research activities of John Rodman Paul. The papers document his work on infectious diseases, principally poliomyelitis, rheumatic fever, hepatitis, and mononucleosis.
Paul, John R. (John Rodman), 1893-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Medical Historical Library, 1980; and from the School of Epidemiology and Public Health, 1994 and 1995.
Associated Materials
Dorothy Millicent Horstmann Papers (MS 1700), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. General Files, 1920-1971. II. Research Files, 1935-1968. III. Writings, 1925-1971. IV. Personal Papers and Photographs, 1920-1992.
Scope and Contents
The John Rodman Paul Papers document Paul's career as a world renowned epidemiologist. They contain professional correspondence with colleagues and institutions, research notebooks and reports, and photographs. Paul's academic responsibilities at the Yale University School of Medicine as professor of preventive medicine and epidemiology are documented, and topical files highlight his work on the epidemiology of bacterial and viral diseases, especially poliomyelitis during the period of the 1930s through the 1960s. The papers include alternative scientific views and quack theories on the causes, prevention, and treatment of poliomyelitis. The papers contain little personal information.
Paul wrote extensively, but the papers do not include manuscripts for most of his work. The researcher can refer to the bibliography published at the time of Paul's retirement for a relatively complete list of his publications. The files do contain correspondence associated with some of these, notably A History of Poliomyelitis and An Account of the American Epidemiological Society.
In view of Paul's importance in the field of public health, there is less material in the papers than one would expect. Paul worked closely with Dorothy Horstmann during his years as administrator and researcher, and as his career was winding down and also after his death, Horstmann took responsibility for responding to some of his correspondence and publication of his remaining manuscripts. The Dorothy Horstmann Papers include additional material relating to the productive collaboration between them.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
John Rodman Paul taught at the Yale School of Medicine for more than thirty years and made critical contributions to understanding the course of viral diseases such as poliomyelitis. He also developed the concept of clinical epidemiology, which became a thriving academic discipline.
Paul was born in Philadelphia on April 18, 1893, to Henry N. Paul and the former Margaret C. Butler. He earned his A.B. in 1915 from Princeton University and his M.D. from Johns Hopkins Medical School in 1919. After serving as an assistant pathologist at Johns Hopkins from 1919 to1920, he interned at the Pennsylvania Hospital in Philadelphia from 1920 to 1922. He remained at the Pennsylvania Hospital until 1928 as director of the Ayer Clinical Laboratory.
In 1928, he came to the Yale School of Medicine as an assistant professor of internal medicine and rose to the position of professor and chairman of the newly created department of preventive medicine in 1940. Paul helped devise the serological test known as the Paul-Bunnell test to identify mononucleosis in 1931. While working on the epidemiology of rheumatic fever with Indian children from Canadian to the Mexican border, he established the role of hemolytic streptococcus in the infection.
In 1931, Paul and colleague Dr. James D. Trask founded the Yale Poliomyelitis Study Unit. In 1938, they received the first research grant from the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, which was renewed annually for thirty years. They identified strains of poliovirus in human waste and found the same strains in sewage.
During World War II, Paul served as director of the Neurotropic Virus Disease Commission of the Armed Forces Epidemiological Board (AFEB). In 1943, Paul headed the Virus Commission, which included Albert Sabin. The commission went to North Africa and while in Egypt confirmed the diagnosis of poliomyelitis among U.S. and British troops. The virus was unknown in the adult Egyptian population, and Paul hypothesized that young Egyptian children acquired immunity after early exposure to the virus, but that the troops who had not been exposed to the virus before contracted polio at a surprising rate. From his later study of Alaskan Eskimos (1949), he made the important discovery that a single experience with poliomyelitis resulted in lifelong immunity. This discovery provided the impetus for the development of immunizing vaccines.
By the 1950s, Paul was a recognized international figure in virology and was asked to serve on committees for the United States Armed Forces, the National Institutes of Health, the World Health Organization and many others. He was appointed by the United States to evaluate the Salk vaccine. He also conducted many of the early tests that confirmed the effectiveness and safety of the Sabin oral vaccine. He stimulated the development of the serum banks from persons of different ages in many different countries in order to establish reference sera for the exploration of epidemiology by serum studies.
After he became professor emeritus in 1961 and until 1966, he was the director of the World Health Organization Serum Reference Bank located in the Yale Department of Epidemiology and Public Health. He was subsequently named lecturer in the history of science and medicine at Yale. His most important contribution during this period was his A History of Poliomyelitis (1971), which chronicled the scientific discoveries and dead ends that slowly led to the complete understanding of this disease.
Paul served as president of the American Society for Clinical Investigation in 1938 and as president of the American College of Physicians from 1955 to 1956. He was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the National Academy of Sciences, the American College of Physicians, and granted honorary membership in the Royal Society of Medicine. Yale created an endowed chair in Paul's name in 1967. He died May 6, 1971.
Clinical epidemiology; Epidemiology -- Study and teaching; Medicine, Preventive; Medicine; Poliomyelitis; Horstmann, Dorothy M. (Dorothy Millicent), 1911-; Paul, John R. (John Rodman), 1893-1971; Yale University. Department of Epidemiology and Public Health; Yale University. School of Medicine. Section of Preventive Medicine
- General Files, 1920-1971, undated; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically, the series consists of Paul's professional correspondence with colleagues, institutions, organizations, and publishers. The files reflect Paul's numerous professional contacts and the depth of his involvement with them. In addition to correspondence, some files contain materials relating to organizational committee work and conferences, such as memoranda, reports, and minutes.
  Through materials filed under the Yale School of Medicine, one can trace the developing specialization in public health, particularly preventive medicine and epidemiology. The series also includes documentation of Paul's long working association with Dorothy Horstmann, both as an administrator and a researcher, but very few other personal letters exist.
  Additional correspondence relating to Paul's publications can be found in Series III.
  - A, 1923-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Abbot, Mandel, 1921-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Academy of Microbiology, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Andrewes, Christopher H., 1941-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Austin, Harold, 1928-1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aycock, W. Lloyd, 1932-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B, 1923-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - Baldwin, Louis B., 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Battles, Winthrop H., 1926-1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bauer, John T., 1925-1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bauer, Walter, 1937-1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bayne-Jones, Stanhope and Nan, 1936-1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Beeson, Paul S., 1953-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Berry, George Packer, 1948-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Blake, Francis G., 1926-1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Blumer, George, 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bronk, Detlev W., 1947-1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bunim, Joseph J., 1939-1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Burnet, Francis MacFarlane, 1939-1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - C, 1922-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 25-28)
  - Caner, G. Colket, Mary, and Emily, 1925-1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Casals, Jordi, 1943-1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Caughey, Jock E., 1947-1958 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Chapin, William E., 1925-1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Clark, E. Gurney, 1944-1962 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Clark, Paul F., 1941-1955 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Coburn, Alvin F., 1924-1958 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Cohn, Alfred E., 1930-1940 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Committee on Enteroviruses, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Conference on Virus and Rickettsial Classification and Nomenclature, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Cummings, Martin M., 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - D, 1923-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 40-43)
  - Dalldorf, Gilbert, 1948-1963 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Davison, Roland, 1937-1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Dedrick, Helen, 1932-1938 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - deForest, Gideon K., 1934-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Dochez, A. R., 1934-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Draper, George, 1933-1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Drinker, Cecil Kent and Katherine Roten, 1923-1956 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Drinker, Phillip, 1925-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Dublin, Louis I., 1930-1945 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Dunham, Charles and Lucia, 1928-1945 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - E, 1922-1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Emerson, Haven, 1930-1967 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Enders, John, 1943-1961 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Evans, Alfred S., 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - F, 1922-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 58-60)
  - Faber, Harry A., 1940-1952 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Farley, David L., 1928-1939 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Flexner, Simon, 1925-1936 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Fox, Elizabeth G., 1932-1949 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Fox, Herbert, 1923-1938 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Francis, Thomas, Jr. and Dorothy, 1938-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Freyberg, Richard E., 1948-1957 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Fulton, John F., 1930-1963 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - G, 1922-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 69-72)
  - Gallagher, J. Roswell, 1948-1951, undated (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Gard, Sven, 1939-1957 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Gear, James H. S., 1947-1959 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Germer, W. D., 1952 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Gilden, Edward and Margaret, 1932-1956 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Ginder, David R., 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Gorham, L. Whittington, 1938-1953 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Graham, Ralph S., 1925-1933 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Green, Robert H., 1950-1960 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - H, 1922-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 82-86)
  - Hadley, Philip, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Hammon, William McD., 1947-1968 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Hanger, Franklin M., 1945-1950, undated (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Hannahan, Edward M., 1927-1951 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Harrell, George T., 1948-1956 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Hatfield, John N., 1933-1938 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Havens, W. Paul, Jr., 1946-1962 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Haviland, James W., 1940-1955 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Haymaker, Webb, 1928-1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Hayman, J. M., Jr., 1929-1958 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Hazard, Thomas Pierpont, 1936-1954 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Hedley, O. F., 1934-1940 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Hench, Philip S., 1934-1950 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Hill, A. Bradford, 1950-1953 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Hiscock, Ira V., 1934-1962 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Horstmann, Dorothy A., 1948-1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 102-103)
  - Howard, Marion Edith, 1945-1959 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Hughes, John, 1948-1964 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Huntington, Robert W., Jr., 1942-1958 (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - Huttrer, Charles P., 1957-1959, undated (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - I, 1926-1962, undated (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - J, 1926-1962, undated (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Janeway, Charles A., 1942-1949 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Jones, T. Duckett, 1930-1949 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Jungeblut, Claus W., 1933-1952 (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - K, 1923-1961 (Box 5, Folder 113-115)
  - Kern, Richard A., 1932-1959 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Kessel, John F., 1934-1948 (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Keynes, Quentin, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Kirkbride, Mary B., 1924-1947 (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Kling, Carl, 1945-1950 (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Korns, Robert F., 1945-1962 (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - Krumbhaar, Edward B., 1924-1947 (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - L, 1922-1967, undated (Box 6, Folder 123-126)
  - Lawrence, John H., 1936-1964 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - Lederle Laboratories, 1937-1952 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - Leonard, John C., 1932-1954 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - Lépine, Pierre, 1939-1956 (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - Ligeti, Armin, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Longcope, Warfield, 1922-1954, undated (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - Loosli, Clayton G., 1949-1961 (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - M, 1925-1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 134-138)
  - MacCallum, William G., 1921-1939, undated (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - MacLeod, Colin, 1951-1963 (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - Matumoto, Minoru, 1951-1956 (Box 6, Folder 141)
  - McClintock, Margaret, 1928-1931 (Box 6, Folder 142)
  - McCown, Albert S., 1927-1953 (Box 6, Folder 143)
  - McFarlan, Allan, 1947-1955 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Means, John Howard, 1931-1961 (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Meenan, Patrick N., 1955-1958 (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - Melnick, Joseph L., 1951-1971 (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - Meyer, Karl F., 1939-1967 (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - Miles, Walter R., 1945-1955 (Box 7, Folder 149)
  - Miller, C. Phillip, 1939-1962 (Box 7, Folder 150)
  - Müller, Friedrich von, 1937-1938 (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - N, 1920-1962 (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1945-1971 (Box 7, Folder 153)
  - National Research Council, 1933-1965 (Box 7, Folder 154-155)
  - New England Postgraduate Assembly, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 156)
  - Newbold, Eugene, 1926, undated (Box 7, Folder 157)
  - Niven, Janet, 1950-1958 (Box 7, Folder 158)
  - Norris, George W., 1926-1931 (Box 7, Folder 159)
  - O, 1930-1957 (Box 7, Folder 160)
  - Opie, Eugene L., 1922-1934 (Box 7, Folder 161)
  - Osborn, Stanley H., 1933-1960 (Box 7, Folder 162)
  - Oughterson, Ashley T., 1936-1956 (Box 7, Folder 163)
  - P, 1922-1969, undated (Box 7, Folder 164-165)
  - P, 1922-1969, undated (Box 8, Folder 166-167)
  - Paul, Henry N., 1925-1956, undated (Box 8, Folder 168)
  - Paul family, 1928-1971, undated (Box 8, Folder 169)
  - Phillips, R. A., 1951-1962 (Box 8, Folder 170)
  - Powers, Grover F., 1932-1961 (Box 8, Folder 171)
  - Q, 1936, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 172)
  - Quinn, Robert W., 1945-1962 (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - R, 1921-1962, undated (Box 8, Folder 174-176)
  - Rhodes, Andrew, 1947-1960 (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - Rich, Arnold R., 1924-1960, undated (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - Richards, Alfred Newton, 1927-1960, undated (Box 8, Folder 179)
  - Rienhoff, William F., Jr., 1925-1949, undated (Box 8, Folder 180)
  - Rivers, Thomas M., 1935-1962 (Box 8, Folder 181)
  - Robinson, G. Candy, 1924-1960 (Box 8, Folder 182)
  - Rose, Samuel Allison, 1940-1951 (Box 8, Folder 183)
  - Rosen, George, 1957-1970 (Box 8, Folder 184)
  - Roten, Katherine
    General note
    See: Series I. General Files Box 3, Folder 50
  - Russell, W. Ritchie, 1948-1955 (Box 8, Folder 185)
  - Rutstein, David D., 1943-1967, undated (Box 8, Folder 186)
  - Ryle, John A. and Miriam, 1947-1950 (Box 8, Folder 187)
  - S, 1922-1964, undated (Box 9, Folder 188-195)
  - Sabin, Albert Bruce, 1941-1967 (Box 9, Folder 196)
  - Salter, William T., 1946-1952 (Box 9, Folder 197)
  - Schier, R., 1946-1958 (Box 9, Folder 198)
  - Simmons, James S., 1944-1954 (Box 9, Folder 199)
  - Smadel, Joseph E., 1949-1963 (Box 9, Folder 200)
  - Smith, R. E., 1934-1957 (Box 9, Folder 201)
  - Stadie, William E., 1929-1946 (Box 9, Folder 202)
  - Stokes, Joseph, Jr., 1931-1961 (Box 9, Folder 203)
  - Stroud, William D., 1928-1954, undated (Box 9, Folder 204)
  - Swift, Homer F., 1928-1953, undated (Box 9, Folder 205)
  - T, 1924-1969, undated (Box 10, Folder 206-208)
  - Tappan, Vivian, 1937-1939, undated (Box 10, Folder 209)
  - Test, Daniel D., 1923-1930 (Box 10, Folder 210)
  - Topping, Norman H., 1943-1958 (Box 10, Folder 211)
  - Trask, James D. and family, 1936-1952, undated (Box 10, Folder 212)
  - U, 1926-1963, undated (Box 10, Folder 213)
  - V, 1925-1960 (Box 10, Folder 214)
  - Van Rooyen, C. E., 1944-1956, undated (Box 10, Folder 215)
  - Verlinde, J. D., 1947-1949 (Box 10, Folder 216)
  - Vickering, Martha K., 1928-1932 (Box 10, Folder 217)
  - Von Magnus, Herdis and Preben, 1947-1956 (Box 10, Folder 218)
  - W, 1921-1970, undated (Box 10, Folder 219-223)
  - Ward, Robert, 1942-1955, undated (Box 11, Folder 224)
  - Watson, Cecil James, 1946-1963 (Box 11, Folder 225)
  - Webster, Leslie T. and Emily, 1923-1967, undated (Box 11, Folder 226)
  - Welt, Louis G., 1941-1952, undated (Box 11, Folder 227)
  - Wenner, Herbert A., 1946-1953 (Box 11, Folder 228)
  - Willard, William R., 1948-1958 (Box 11, Folder 229)
  - Wilson, James L., 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 230)
  - Winslow, Charles-Edward A., 1931-1962 (Box 11, Folder 231)
  - Winternitz, Milton C. and Elizabeth, 1928-1950, undated (Box 11, Folder 232)
  - World Health Organization. Reference Serum Bank, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 233)
  - Wright, Sidney J., Jr., 1924-1931 (Box 11, Folder 234)
  - Wyatt, H. V., 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 235)
  - Y, 1941-1958 (Box 11, Folder 236)
  - Yale University
    - General, 1933-1952, undated (Box 11, Folder 237)
    - Yale School of Medicine
      - Department of History of Science and Medicine, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 238)
      - Medical School Council, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 239)
      - Poliomyelitis exhibition, 1949-1950 (Box 11, Folder 240)
      - Section of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine
        - Annual reports, 1956-1961 (Box 11, Folder 241-244)
        - Memoranda, 1947-1955, undated (Box 11, Folder 245)
      - Section of Preventive Medicine
        - Annual reports, 1942-1956 (Box 12, Folder 246-251)
        - Interdepartmental meetings, [1952]-1955 (Box 12, Folder 252)
        - Reports, 1940-1956 (Box 12, Folder 253)
        - Staff meeting minutes, 1954-1961 (Box 12, Folder 254-255)
        - Teaching, 1951-1960, undated (Box 12, Folder 256)
  - Z, 1931-1955 (Box 12, Folder 257)
  - Unidentified, 1927-1969, undated (Box 12, Folder 258)
- Research Files, 1935-1968, undated; Series II
  The series is arranged alphabetically by topic and includes correspondence, research data, notebooks, and reports. The materials include documentation of Paul's investigative efforts on encephalitis and hemorrhagic fever, but the bulk of the material concerns studies on poliomyelitis. Materials filed under the Alaska heading relate to poliomyelitis but document a specific serological investigation of antibody levels of an isolated Eskimo population. The other poliomyelitis files cover a broader time span and include correspondence from both professionals and lay people, reflecting alternative views on the causes, prevention, and treatment of polio. The polio files also include some of Paul's research data and research reports regarding his studies. Controversies over prevention, specifically the type of vaccine are represented in the files on vaccines.
  The hemorrhagic fever files document studies in Korea and New Haven.
  - Alaska
    - Poliomyelitis epidemic, [1951-1961], undated (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
      General
      See also: Series III. Writings, Box 18, Folder 8
    - Serological project, 1948-1950 (Box 13, Folder 4-8)
      See also: Series III. Writings, Box 8, Folder 9
  - Encephalitis
    - Eastern equine encephalitis, 1957 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Lethargica, Undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Hemorrhagic fever
    - Correspondence, 1949-1959 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Experimental data and notes, 1953, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Commission on Hemorrhagic Fever. Second annual report., 1953-1954 (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
      See also: Series III. Writings, Box 8, Folder 12
  - Poliomyelitis
    - Alternative views of cause and treatment
      - General, 1948-1964, undated (Box 14, Folder 15-17)
      - Dilworth, John I., 1953, undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
      - Fitzman, Marsh, 1948-1955 (Box 14, Folder 19)
      - Miller, Duon, 1952-1953 (Box 14, Folder 20)
      - Paul, Ernest, 1956-1957 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Classification and nomenclature of the virus, 1952-1958 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - England poliomyelitis epidemic, 1947-1949 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis
      - General, 1944-1968 (Box 15, Folder 24)
      - Round Table Conference: "Importance of Insects in the Transmission of Poliomyelitis", 1948 (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Research data
      - Experimental poliomyelitis, 1936-1939 (Box 15, Folder 26-28)
      - Experimental poliomyelitis, 1940-1941 (Box 16, Folder 29)
      - In birds, 1943-1947 (Box 16, Folder 30)
      - Miami, 1941-1942 (Box 16, Folder 31-32)
      - Polio strains, 1935-1936 (Box 16, Folder 33)
    - Research reports, 1950, 1958-1960 (Box 16, Folder 34-35)
      See also: Series III. Writings, Box 18, Folder 22
      See also: Series III. Writings, Box 18, Folder 17
      See also: Series III. Writings, Box 18, Folder 15
      See also: Series III. Writings, box 18, Folder 10
    - State planning, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - Vaccines
      - Conferences, 1960 (Box 17, Folder 37)
      - Surgeon General's Committee on Poliomyelitis Control, 1960-1962 (Box 17, Folder 38-42)
      - Shannon/O'Connor controversy on development of poliomyelitis vaccine, 1966-1967 (Box 17, Folder 43)
- Writings, 1925?-1971, undated; Series III
  Arranged chronologically, the series consists of manuscripts for John Rodman Paul's unpublished lectures and addresses, as well as for works not listed in the bibliography published in The Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, vol 34, no.3-4, (1961 Dec.-1962 Feb.) The series also includes correspondence relating to publication and contracts. The extensive correspondence associated with Paul's research for An Account of the American Epidemiological Society is also in this series. Drafts and reprints of published writings have not been retained.
  - "Lobar Pneumonia at the Pennsylvania Hospital, 1925" (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - "Tumors of the Breast" [lecture], 1928 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Lecture to premedical students, University of Arizona, 1937 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Address to American Society of Clinical Investigation, 1938 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Hepatitis talk [American Medical Association, Chicago], 1944 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - "Recent Advances in Infectious Hepatitis and Related Forms of Acute Forms of Hepatitis" [lecture, New England Postgraduate Assembly], [1946] (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Gehrman lectures, 1947 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - "Antibodies to Various Strains of Poliomyelitis Virus in Sera from North Alaska Eskimos" [with J. L. Melnick], [1949] (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - "Considerations with Regard to Epidemiological Investigations at the Arctic Research Laboratory", 1949 (Box 18, Folder 9)